Well, welcome back to Jupyter Lab for what will be an epic finale to our time in this platform.
주피터 연구소에 잘 오셨습니다 이 플랫폼에서 보낸 시간의 에픽 엔딩이 될 텐데요
And it's going to be such a great conclusion to the last seven weeks.
지난 7주간의 멋진 마무리가 될 거예요
The first thing you'll notice is that there is quite a lot going on in the week eight folder.
가장 먼저 눈에 띄는 건 8주 차 폴더에 많은 일이 벌어지고 있다는 거예요
There are a lot of files here, which reflects the fact that we've got a lot to get through, a lot
여기 파일이 많은 건 우리가 풀어야 할 게 많다는 걸 보여주죠 이 큰 문제를 해결하기 위해
of work to be done to solve this big problem.
해야 할 일이 많다는 걸요 Get it
It means I'm going to be moving at a faster pace than usual as we go through this code.
이 코드가 진행되는 동안 평소보다 더 빠른 속도로 움직일 거라는 의미죠
But that's okay, because at this point you are proficient, you're well on your way to mastering LLM
하지만 괜찮습니다 지금 시점에서는 이미 능숙하고 LLM 엔지니어링의 달인이 되어
engineering, and you no longer need me to belabor the point about lists of dicts of assistants and
가고 있으니까요 이제 제가 설명할 필요도 없겠죠 조수와 사용자 같은 사람들이 어디에
users and things like that.
있는지에 대해서요
It's it's now something that is very much old news.
이제는 아주 오래된 뉴스죠
And yeah, it's amazing to think I was explaining what tokens were only, only a matter of weeks ago.
네, 토큰이 뭔지 설명하고 있었는데 불과 몇 주 전이었다니 놀랍죠
And and now that you're ready for a big, full on agentic AI I.
이제 에이전트 같은 인공지능 1을 경험할 준비가 됐어요
Solution a quick admin point before we get started.
시작 전에 get 절차가 있어요
Uh, the I've made some changes to the packages.
패키지를 좀 바꿨어요
I've added some more packages that are dependencies on this environment in order to, to really make
이 환경에 종속성이 있는 패키지를 추가했어요 이걸 아주 흥미로운 문제로
this a very, very juicy problem.
만들기 위해서요
And that just means you might need if you've if you pulled the code sometime before like late September,
그 말은 여러분이∙∙∙ 9월 말쯤에 코드를 불러오면 다시 코드를 불러와 패키지를
you might need to pull the code again and update your packages to have anything new that I've added.
업데이트해야 할 수도 있어요 제가 추가한 새로운 게 있으려면요
And that's very easy to do.
아주 쉬운 일이죠
Um, all you have to do, of course, is go to the project home directory.
여러분이 할 일은 프로젝트 홈 디렉터리에 가는 거죠
So LM engineering.
LM 엔지니어링이죠
Um, and if you're on a PC, then you need to be in an Anaconda prompt.
PC용이라면 아나콘다 프롬프트가 있어야 해요
Uh, and then you do a git pull to get the latest code, and then you run conda env update.
최신 코드를 얻기 위해 깃 풀을 하고 콘다 인플루언서 업데이트를 실행해요
Um, you specify the file as environment.yml and the dash dash prune tells it to remove any packages
파일을 환경으로 지정해요 yml과 prune은 목록에 없는 패키지를
that are no longer in the list.
제거하라고 하죠
I don't think I have removed anything, but anyways, I think this is always a sensible uh, one liner.
아무것도 삭제하지 않은 것 같아요 어쨌든 이건 항상 실용적인 한 줄 대사예요
Good to have that to hand to update your environment with a new environment.yml file.
새로운 환경으로 환경을 업데이트하는 데 필요한 거죠 yml 파일이요
Okay, so here we go.
자, 시작하죠
Let's talk about modal.
수법에 대해 얘기해보죠
So as we get into today's class there only is one import to begin with.
오늘 수업에 들어서면서 get은 하나만 남았어요
And it is to import modal.
수단을 들여오는 거죠
There we go.
됐어요
Now if you have not set up your tokens which you will not have done, then you need to run a command
토큰을 설정하지 않았다면 모듈 셋업이라는 명령줄을 실행해야
line thing called modal setup.
해요
And the way you can run that is you just uncomment this line and you run that statement right there.
실행 방법은 이 줄을 주석 처리 해제하고 저 문을 저기서 실행하는 거죠
Now I'm not going to do it because I've already done it and my environment set up.
지금은 안 할게요 이미 해뒀거든요 환경 설정도요
But when you do, it's going to pop up with a browser window and have you authorize modal.
하지만 그렇게 하면 브라우저 창이 뜨고 양식을 승인하게 돼요
And then modal will set your environment variables for you.
그럼 Modal이 환경 변수를 설정해 주죠
And I think that's really great.
정말 멋진 것 같아요
All of the challenges that people have had with tokens, particularly with OpenAI, this is a very different
토큰을 가지고 겪는 어려움들 특히 오픈아이는 완전히 다른 경험이에요
It's really streamlined.
아주 간소화됐죠
So good for modal.
수법에 아주 좋죠
They seem to have really figured out the the way to set tokens.
패를 놓는 법을 제대로 터득한 것 같군요
If for any reason that doesn't work for you, then if you go into the modal platform, you can actually
만약 그게 안 된다면 표준 플랫폼으로 가보세요 거기서 여러분의 토큰을 찾을
find your tokens in there in much the same way as you can for for things like OpenAI.
수 있어요 OpenAI 같은 걸 위한 것과 거의 같은 방식으로요
And then you can manually set it.
수동으로 설정할 수 있어요
Um, but hopefully this will just work.
그래도 잘되면 좋겠어요
It certainly did for me.
전 그랬어요
And by all accounts, that's that's how it works for for people generally.
누가 봐도 일반적으로 사람들이 그렇게 하죠
All right.
좋아요
So now, uh, in the next line, I'm going to import some things from a package called hello, which
이제 다음 줄에서 hello라는 패키지에서 몇 가지를 불러오겠습니다 여기
is just what I've written over here.
적어둔 거죠
And I'm going to take you over to that right now to show you what it looks like.
지금 당장 가서 어떻게 생겼는지 보여드릴게요
So this is just a piece of Python.
이건 파이썬 일부분이에요
It's just some, some Python code.
파이썬 으로 된 코드네요
And I'm going to tell you what it does.
이게 뭘 하는지 말씀드리죠
So we import modal.
그래서 모듈을 수입하죠
And from modal we import a few things.
몇 가지를 수입했어요
App for applications volume and image.
앱 볼륨과 이미지를 위한 앱이요
Um and actually now that I look at it I see that I don't actually end up using volume.
사실 지금 보니까 볼륨을 사용하지 않았네요
So I don't think that is needed.
그래서 그건 필요 없다고 생각해요
Keep this simple is better.
간단한 게 좋아요
Um, and so this is what you do.
그래서 이렇게 해요
You begin with some setup.
설정으로 시작해요
You tell modal what kind of infrastructure you need.
어떤 인프라가 필요한지 설명하는 거죠
And this is an example of modal talks about this a bit on the in their docs.
이건 모듈의 예입니다 문서에서 비트로 언급하죠
But this is this is a type of infrastructure as code.
이건 코드로서의 인프라 유형이에요
You can use code to describe what kind of box you want.
어떤 박스를 원하는지 코드를 사용해 설명할 수 있어요
So if you're thinking when we're in Google Colab, we had to pick various drop downs and choose what
Google Colab에서 다양한 드롭다운을 선택해야 한다고 생각하신다면
kind of, um, VM, what runtime we wanted from Google Colab, well, here you just get to choose what
어떤 종류의 VM을 선택해야 하는지 Google Colab에서 어떤 런타임을 원하는지 말이에요 여기선 코드에서 지정해
you want by by specifying it in code.
원하는 걸 선택할 수 있어요
So we, we say that we want an image which we want it to be the Debian operating system.
이미지가 필요하다고 하면 그게 데비언 운영체제가 되어야죠
We want to pip install the requests package that very, very common standard package for, for uh,
요청 패키지를 설치하려고 합니다 URL 웹 작업을 위한 아주 아주
doing URL web work.
일반적인 표준 패키지죠
Um, and we specify a GPU, uh, actually, which again is also not used in this example.
GPU를 명시합니다 이 예제에선 사용되지 않았죠
Sorry.
미안해요
That makes it a bit simpler.
비트가 더 간단하죠
We're not going to use a GPU for this example because we're keeping it very simple indeed.
이 예제에서는 GPU 사용은 안 할 겁니다 아주 단순하게 할 거니까요
Uh, so uh, the I have got a method called hello.
그래서 전 인사법을 알아요
It's a very simple.
아주 간단해요
It's a function.
일종의 함수예요
Hello.
안녕하세요
That returns a string.
문자열을 반환하죠
Uh, and what it does is it imports requests, uh, it gets it goes to a website called IP info.io,
이것은 불러오기 요청을 합니다 IP 정보라는 웹사이트로 가죠 io는 알아두면 유용하죠
It's just one of these utilities that will return a JSON object which describes where you are the IP
JSON 객체를 반환하는 유틸리티 중 하나로 IP 주소를
address of, of what just called it.
설명하는 거죠
Um, and so then I take that JSON, I pull out the city, the region and the country, and I say hello
그리고 JSON을 가져다가 도시, 지역, 나라를 뽑고 도시, 지역, 나라에서
from city, region, country.
인사를 해요
Um, and it's just based on your IP address.
IP 주소로 판단한 거예요
So it's just going to say hello from wherever you are, or at least wherever your ISP is serving you
여러분이 어디 있든 안녕하세요를 할 겁니다 적어도 ISP가 서빙하는 곳에서요
from.
그래서 뉴욕과 가까운 곳에 갈 거예요 뉴욕이 아닐 수도 있고요
Um, so that's a pretty simple function.
아주 간단한 함수예요
The only potential interesting thing about it is this decorator at the top here, which is a gradient
잠재적으로 흥미로운 건 여기 위에 있는 장식가예요 앱으로 장식한
decorator where we've decorated it with app, which is this thing here, this modal app.
그러데이션 장식가죠 여기 이거요 모달 앱이요
Hello dot function.
Hello.com 함수요
And then we're passing in this image.
이 이미지를 전달해요
And that image refers to a Debian image uh which has requests installed.
그 이미지는 디비언 이미지를 뜻해요 요청이 설치된 이미지죠
And just by decorating it with that, we're saying that's the kind of box that we want to be to be able
그렇게 장식한다는 건 우리가 원할 경우 실행할 수 있는 그런 종류의 박스가
to run this on should we wish to.
되기를 원한다는 거죠
That's all there is to it.
그게 다예요
So you you could put that to one side.
그래서 그건 한쪽에 두죠 Put
You could imagine that this was just part of an existing piece of code.
이게 현존하는 코드의 일부라고 상상할 수 있어요
You had to do something, and now you've just decorated it with something to say that you want to be
뭔가를 해야만 했고 이젠 실행하고 싶다고 말할 수 있는 것으로
able to run it should you wish to, using a Debian operating system with requests installed.
장식했어요 요청이 설치된 디비언 운영체제를 사용해서요
So that is all that's in this hello.py.
이 안에 있는 건 그게 다예요 네
Super simple.
아주 간단해요
We go back to day one dot, the Jupyter notebook.
첫째 날 점으로 돌아가죠 주피터 공책요
So I'm now going to import that.
이제 그걸 불러오죠
And so now what I can do is I can call my hello I can I can take my hello function that I've, that
이제 hello를 호출할 수 있습니다 여기 가져오기 한 hello 함수를
I've imported here.
취할 수 있어요
And I can call it by saying hello dot local.
hello. local이라고 입력하면 돼요
And what that means is I want to run that function that I've just defined, that we just looked at this
그 말은 방금 정의한 저 함수를 실행하고 싶다는 거죠 방금 이 함수를 본 거요
function here, and I just want to run it on my local box.
제 로컬 상자에서 실행하고 싶다는 거죠
I want to run it in this Jupyter notebook.
이 주피터 공책에 넣고 싶어요
Let's see what we get.
get get을 해 보죠
So it's running right now.
지금 실행 중이에요
And it says hello from seaport, New York, US.
뉴욕 시포트에서 인사하는 거예요
That is where my ISP is, I guess.
제 ISP가 거기 있나 봐요
Let's try that again.
다시 해 보죠
Yeah, that seems pretty consistent.
네, 일관성이 있네요
So that's running locally.
로컬에서 실행되고 있어요
Uh, and, uh, now look at this one here.
그리고 이 사진을 보세요
It's exactly the same thing.
완전히 똑같아요
I've just changed local to remote.
로컬에서 원격으로 바꿨어요
That's the only.
그게 다예요
The only thing I've changed.
유일하게 변한 거죠
Let's see what happens.
어떻게 되나 보죠
Let's take a little bit longer and then.
조금만 더 비트를 타 보죠
Hello from Ashburn, Virginia, us.
버지니아 애시번에서 인사드려요
It's running in a completely different state, so I'm sure you you're expecting that.
완전히 다른 상태에서 실행되고 있어요 그러니 그걸 기대하시겠죠
You get the idea.
Get it, Get it 아시겠죠?
Uh, and sometimes it's different.
가끔은 다르기도 해요
By the way, I've seen it pop up all over the place.
그나저나 여기저기서 나오는 걸 봤어요
So simply by calling remote instead of local, you can call this function the same piece of code, the
로컬 대신 원격 호출을 하면 이 함수를 같은 코드 조각으로 호출할 수 있습니다 파이썬 코드와
same piece of Python code.
같은 거죠
And it's been deployed to a server and it's running on that server instead.
서버에 배포되어 그 서버에서 실행되고 있죠
So I think that's pretty magical.
정말 마법 같은 일이죠
It's magical because it's so simple and it's just allowed us to deploy some code.
마법 같아요 아주 간단하고 코드 몇 개를 배포하게 해주거든요
And now we've got a slightly more involved package called llama.
지금은 라마라는 좀 더 복잡한 패키지를 만들고 있어요
And this is where things like GPUs start to appear.
여기서 GPU 같은 게 나타나기 시작하죠
You can see I paired this back to the hello example, which is why there was some some traces of what
보다시피 hello 예제와 연결했어요 그래서 이게 무엇이었는지에 대한 흔적이 있었던
this was.
거죠
Um, so I start by, um, uh, calling my app llama.
우선 제 앱 라마에게 전화를 걸어요
Um, now I'm going to again have a Debian image, but this time I'm going to install torch transformers,
디비언 이미지도 넣는데 이번에는 토치 트랜스포머 비트, 바이트
bits and bytes and accelerate all packages that you know.
패키지 가속도 전부 넣을 거예요
Well, at this point, um, I am also getting my hugging face token from my modal secrets, and that
지금 저는 포옹하는 얼굴 토큰도 받고 있어요 제 방식의 비밀에서요 진작 보여 드렸어야
is something I should have shown you before.
하는 거죠
I will show you in a second how you set that up in modal, how you get to secrets, and you can set
잠시 후 Modal에서 그걸 설정하는 방법을 보여드릴게요 기밀에 도달하는 방법과 포옹하는
your hugging face token in there.
얼굴 토큰을 설정하는 방법도요
And once you've done that, you can read it like this.
그렇게 하고 나면 이렇게 읽을 수 있어요
And I'm specifying that I want a T4 GPU, which of course is the very cheap basic one.
T4 GPU를 원한다고 지정하고 있어요 물론 아주 저렴한 기본이죠
And I've got a constant here.
여기 상속자가 있어요
And now I have uh, this, this generate, uh, function.
이제 생성 함수가 있네요
And it takes a prompt which is a string, and it returns a string.
문자열인 프롬프트를 받아 문자열을 반환하죠
This is an example of the type hints.
힌트 형식의 예시인데요
If you're not familiar with them.
잘 모르신다면요
It's something that I'll be doing this time around in various places.
이번에는 여러 곳에서 할 거예요
And it will, uh, I think, become clear after a bit.
비트만 좀 있으면 분명해질 거예요
So, uh, again, I decorate this function with I pass in the image, I tell it my secrets, and I say
이 함수도 장식했어요 이미지를 전달하고 비밀을 말하고 T4 GPU를
I want a T4 GPU, all configuring my server using code.
원한다고 했죠 코드를 이용해 서버를 구성해요
And now this is just a function as if I were writing something to run locally.
이건 로컬에서 실행할 뭔가를 작성하는 함수예요
Now, I couldn't possibly run this locally because my box has nothing like the horsepower to be able
이걸 로컬에서 실행할 순 없어요 제 박스는 이런 llama 모델을
to run a llama model like this locally.
로컬에서 실행할 만한 힘이 없거든요
There are ways you can do it with things like llama CP if you're familiar with that, but I wouldn't
라마 CP 같은 것으로도 할 수 있는 방법이 있어요 익숙하신지 모르겠지만
be able to do it like it's written here, and if I did, it would be very, very slow.
여기 쓰여 있는 대로는 못 할 거예요 한다고 해도 아주 느릴 거고요
Um, and so I want to do it on a box which has a T4 GPU and this is how I'll be able to do it.
T4 GPU가 있는 박스에서 작업하고 싶어요 이렇게 하는 거죠
Um, and so this, this code should all look very familiar to you.
이 코드는 아주 익숙하실 거예요
This is the config that you know.
여러분이 아는 구성이죠
Well that puts specifies the, the four bit quantization that will have for Lama.
그럼 라마를 위한 네 개의 퀀타이즈 비트를 구체적으로 설명해야겠네요
Um, we are going to load the tokenizer, this boilerplate stuff, you know.
토큰라이저를 로드할 거예요 상용문서 같은 거요
Well we are going to load our model.
모델을 로드할 거예요
And then this, you should also recognize we encode the the prompt into tokens as our input.
그리고 프롬프트를 토큰으로 인코딩한 것도 볼 수 있는데요
We set this attention mask to avoid getting that warning.
그런 경고를 피하려고 주의 마스크를 씌웠어요
And then we do model dot generate.
그리고 Model.생성기를 하죠
We pass in our inputs.
입력값을 통과시키죠
We say we only need five new tokens and we want to just one response.
새 토큰 5개만 필요하고 응답은 하나만 필요하다고 하죠
We will take that one response, we will decode it and we will return it.
그 응답을 받아들여서 해독한 다음 돌려주는 거죠
It's as simple as that.
아주 간단해요
Now with that, let's start that and let's run it.
이제 그걸 시작해 실행해보죠
So stuff is happening.
무슨 일이 일어나고 있어요
So, um, first of all, what what have I actually run?
우선, 제가 실제로 실행한 건 뭐죠?
So I've called the remote function and what I passed in the prompt that I passed in to a llama model
원격 함수를 호출했고 프롬프트에서 라마 모델로 보낸 건
is life is a mystery.
삶은 미스터리예요
Everyone must stand alone.
모두 혼자 서야 해요
I hear now, uh, I, uh, hopefully most people know what comes next from that.
이다음은 어떻게 될지 다들 아셨으면 좋겠네요
Otherwise I'm going to feel very old.
안 그러면 제가 늙었다고 느낄 거예요
Uh, but, uh uh, this, of course, would be straight from the opening to Like a Prayer by Madonna.
하지만 이건 물론 오프닝부터 마돈나의 기도처럼 이어지죠
And I hear you Call my name would be what comes next.
내 이름을 부르는 소리가 들리면 그때 부를게요
And it's almost unbearable not to say that.
그 말을 안 하는 게 너무 힘들어요
Uh, and now I'm going to hear that song in my head for for the rest of the day.
이제 그 노래가 제 머릿속에서 오늘 하루 동안 들릴 거예요 HOLO
Uh, but, um.
하지만요
Yeah.
네
And sorry if I've put that now in your in your mind forever too, but, uh, such a catchy song.
이 노래를 영원히 마음에 담아뒀다면 미안해요 하지만 노래가 정말 중독성 있어요 Put it's go
Anyway, it's what we're seeing now is what's going on on that box.
어쨌든 지금 보이는 건 저 상자에서 일어나는 일이에요
Um, and we can also flip over to, to modal itself.
그 자체로 수정할 수도 있어요
Um, and uh, let's see, go to the let me refresh this screen.
그리고 어디 보자 화면을 새로 고침할게요
Uh, so it's not a deployed app.
배포된 앱이 아니에요
Ephemeral apps.
하루살이 앱요
That's what it is.
바로 그거예요
Uh, give me a second to find that.
잠시만요, 좀 찾아볼게요
So this is it.
이게 끝이군요
Running right now.
지금 뛰어요
Running as an ephemeral app, uh, generates, um, started two minutes ago.
단기간 앱으로 운영되는데 2분 전에 시작됐어요
And we can click into it and we can see that its status is running.
클릭하면 상태가 실행 중인 걸 볼 수 있죠
Uh, and, uh, let's see what else we can get.
또 뭐가 있나 볼게요 get it
So the containers, it's live.
컨테이너는 작동해요
We can look at the memory, the CPU cores.
메모리와 CPU 코어를 볼 수 있어요
And we can see it's a T4 GPU, just as we specified.
T4 GPU가 보이죠 우리가 명시한 대로요
Um, and we can also look at the we can see that Hello.py is also on this box we just ran.
그리고 또 볼 수 있는 게 안녕하세요 이 상자에 파이가 있어요
And llama.py uh, is sitting there, the, the Python script that we just wrote.
라마도요 파이썬 파이썬의 대본 스크립트가 거기 있어요
Uh, so here we go.
자, 시작하죠
While we're here, I'm just going to point out that right at the top here is secrets.
여기 온 김에 하나만 지적할게요 맨 위에 있는 건 비밀이에요
And secrets is, of course, where you go to set the secrets, the hugging face token.
비밀은 물론 비밀을 설정하는 곳이죠 포옹 얼굴 토큰이에요
So you will need to do that.
그러니 그렇게 하세요
I'm not going to click on that now to avoid revealing my hugging face token secret.
지금은 클릭하지 않을 거예요 포옹 얼굴 토큰 비밀이 드러나면 안 되니까요
Um, but that's that's where you would go so that you can then use your hugging face token in the code
어쨌든 거기로 가면 됩니다 포옹하는 얼굴 토큰을 사용할 수 있는데
that's deployed in your ephemeral, uh, service here.
그 코드는 여기서 잠깐 동안 배포되는 코드예요
So it's still running.
아직 작동하는군요
And I think at this point I will hold to this video.
이 시점에서 이 비디오를 고수해야겠네요
And when I come back, uh oh, it's already just said it's succeeded.
제가 돌아오면 이미 성공했다고 나오네요
Uh, and I did just get a message saying that it had finished as well.
Get it가 끝났다는 메시지를 받았어요
Uh, and, uh.
그리고요
Let's see.
어디 보죠
Yes.
네
Back here.
여기요
Let's see what we get.
get get을 해 보죠
I hear you call my name.
내 이름을 부르는 소리가 들려요
Uh, so, lama, even the four bit quantized version of Lama also couldn't resist completing the Madonna
네 개의 퀀트화된 라마의 비트조차 마돈나 노래를 완성하지 않을
song as well.
수 없었죠
Uh, and so we have just successfully run this piece of code.
이 코드를 성공적으로 실행했어요
Um, using this ephemeral, uh, service on modal, uh, to run a quantized lama, um, uh, model,
이 단기적인 서비스를 이용해 퀀타이즈한 라마 모델 라마3를 작동했어요
All right.
프롬프트를 완료하는 건 1가지 모델이죠
When we come back, we are going to go through and it's going to be time for us to deploy our model
돌아와서 살펴보고 모델을 배포할 시간이 될 겁니다 어떻게
and actually see how we do that and how we put an API around the proprietary model that we built last
하는지 지난 시간에 빌드한 소유 모델에 API를 어떻게 놓는지 보죠
I will see you in a minute.
잠시 후에 뵙죠